hey guys this looks like a fun one this
is another Katrina a puzzle it's given
us that this is made up of five squares
and it wants to know what's the total
shaded area if you want to try this on
your own pause it right now cuz I'm
going to solve it in 3 2 1 first I want
to look at these three angles they're
going to add up to
180° and that's the same thing as a
triangle so if we look at this triangle
on the left here this right angle can be
brought here and the purple angle can be
brought there these three angles will
also add up to 180° and then we can do
the same thing for this triangle over
here this blue right angle can go here
and then that means that this last angle
would have to be the green angle so
these two triangles have three congruent
angles that means the two triangles are
similar next let's focus on this literal
triangle let's label this side a this
side B and this hypotenuse C well this C
is also one of the sides of these
squares so another side of the square
would also be C in fact all of these
sides would be equal to C I don't think
there's anything else I know for now so
let's pull out these triangles and if we
rotate this one now the two similar
triangles are oriented the same let's
change these four C's into 4 C and now
since these are similar triangles we can
find the scale factor from C to 4 C that
means our scale factor is four to get
the base we're going to multiply a * 4
to get 4 a and to get this height we're
going to multiply B * 4 to get 4 B and
now we know these sides so we can update
this figure let's rotate this triangle
back and you can see that the 4B goes
there and the 4 a goes there so that
looks pretty good now we have three
different ways to measure the side of
this larger Square let's set them equal
to each other so we'll have this side a
+ 4 b equal to this side 4 a and then we
can also do this side b + 13 equal to
this side 4 a and now we have two
equations and two variables so we can
solve for both A and B let's start with
this one we can subtract a from both
sides and that gives us 4 B is equal to
3 a and next we can divide both sides by
four and that will give us B is equal to
34s a and this looks important so let's
put a box around it next let's look at
this equation let's copy it down and in
the place of the B we're going to plug
in 3/4s a and then we want to combine
like terms so let's subtract 34s a from
both sides of the equation on the right
hand side these are going to cancel each
other out and on the left hand side
we're going to do 4 A minus 34s a in
order to subtract these let's give them
a common denominator let's rewrite this
4 as 164s and then we're going to do
164s a - 3 4 a which is equal to 134s a
now to get the a all by itself we'll
multiply both sides by the reciprocal
413 on the left hand side these are
going to cancel each other out and on
the right hand side these two 13s will
cancel each other out so we end up with
a is equal to four and this looks
important so let's put a box around it
now going back to our previous box we
know B is equal to 34s of a a is equal
to four so in the place of this a let's
plug in four and then when we multiply
this 34s * 4 four the fours are going to
cancel each other out we end up with B
is equal to 3 in the place of both of
these A's we can plug in four and then 4
* 4 is equal to 16 and in the place of
both of these B's we can plug in three
and 4 * 3 is equal to 12 so now let's
focus on this little triangle right here
this is a special triangle it's called a
Pythagorean triple anytime a right
triangle has legs three and four the
hypotenuse will always be five and since
this side is five that means this side
is also five and the area of this Square
would be 5 * 5 which is 25 and 25 would
be the area of all these squares so if
we want the area of the Shaded region
we're going to do 4 * 25 and 4 * 25 is
100 and that is the answer to our
question let's put a box around it how
exciting